{"tossups": [{"question": "The Mitterrand Doctrine provided amnesty for members of this group who had renounced violence. This group carried out its most famous action to oppose attempts at a \u201chistoric compromise\u201d. This group\u2019s deadliest act was the bombing of the Central Train Station in Bologna. Mario Moretti led this group, which primarily operated during the Years of Lead. For ten points, name this group of Italian communists who kidnapped and murdered Prime Minister Aldo Moro in 1978.", "answer": "<b> Red Brigades</b> (or<b> Brigate Rosse</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This successor of John Smith was investigated after his party accepted loans in exchange for peerage appointments in the Cash for Honours scandal. This proponent of a \u201cThird way\u201d between capitalism and socialism mediated the Good Friday Agreement, which ended the Troubles in Northern Ireland. This Prime Minister backed George W. Bush\u2019s invasions of Afghanistan and Iraq. For ten points, name this\u201cNew Labour\u201d Prime Minister of Great Britain from 1997 to 2007.", "answer": "Tony<b> Blair</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This speaker noted \u201cI want [slavery] root and branch destroyed\u201d in an 1867 speech to the American Equal Rights Association that ended with a singing of \u201cWe are going home.\u201d This speaker asked \u201cWhere did your Christ come from?\u201d, noting \u201cMan had nothing to do with Him!\u201d in another speech; in that speech, she proclaimed \u201cI have plowed and planted, [...] and no man could head me!\u201d for ten points, name this 19th century activist and orator, a former slave who repeated the question \u201cAin\u2019t I a Woman?\u201d in her most famous speech.", "answer": "Sojourner<b> Truth</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Due to costs, Canadian Prime Minister John Diefenbaker scrapped one of these technologies, the Avro Arrow. One example of this technology, which crashed in a Paris exhibition in 1973, was the Tupolev Tu-144; the only other commercial use of this type of vehicle ended after a 2000 disaster, also in Paris. The Bell X-1, piloted by Chuck Yaeger, was the first example of, for ten points, what type of aircraft that can surpass Mach 1?", "answer": "<b> supersonic</b> aircraft (accept descriptions of an airplane that can<b> break the speed of sound</b>, including<b> break Mach 1</b> before it\u2019s mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader had a nuclear bunker built in the town of Gbadolite. This leader was personally protected by the Special Presidential Division, and changed his name to refer to him going \u201cfrom conquest to conquest, leaving fire in his wake\u201d in the \u201cAuthenticity\u201d campaign. This ruler came to power at the end of a civil war sparked by the secession of the Katanga region, but Laurent Desire-Kabila overthrew him during the First Congo War. For ten points, name this former dictator of Zaire.", "answer": "<b> Mobutu</b> Sese Seko", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this South Vietnamese capital city, now named for Ho Chi Minh, whose fall marked the end of the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b> Saigon</b> (prompt on Ho Chi Minh City before his name is mentioned) <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "While playing against one team from this city in 2012, Joey Barton earned a 12-game suspension for attacking Carlos Tevez, Vincent Kompany, and Sergio Aguero. In that game, Aguero\u2019s 94th minute goal for a team from this city defeated Queens Park Rangers to clinch a title at the expense of another team from this city. That team from this city has suffered under managers David Moyes and Louis van Gaal since the 2013 retirement of Sir Alex Ferguson. For ten points, name this English city whose rival clubs, City and United, have won fifteen of the 23 Premier League titles.", "answer": "<b> Manchester</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This event prevented a plebiscite proposed by Kurt Schuschnigg [shush-nig]. The Mauthausen-Gusen camp was established shortly after this event, which was declared null and void by the Moscow Declaration. This event was encouraged by Arthur Seyss-Inquart, and led to the resignation of President Wilhelm Miklas. This event established the province of Ostmark under the justification of<em> lebensraum</em>, and was followed by the annexation of the Sudetenland. Germany annexed Austria. For ten points, name this 1938 event in which Nazi", "answer": "<b> Anschluss</b> (accept<b> Nazi annexation of Austria</b> before 1938 is mentioned, prompting on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader was first elected as part of the Fifth Republic Movement. This leader called Vincente Fox\u201cthe puppy dog of the empire.\u201d During an Ibero-American Summit, King Juan Carlos I asked this leader\u201cWhy don\u2019t you shut up?\u201d This leader\u2019s funding led to the establishment of the TeleSUR TV network. He\u2019s not Evo Morales, but this leader promoted \u201cSocialism in the 21st century\u201d as part of his Bolivarian Revolution. For ten points, name this socialist President of Venezuela during most of the 2000s.", "answer": "Hugo<b> Chavez</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man noted \u201cyour eyes and mine are never destined to see [the] miracle\u201d of \u201cpeaceable secession\u201din a \u201cplea for Harmony and Peace.\u201d That speech, given on the seventh of March, controversially supported the Compromise of 1850, leading to this man\u2019s resignation from the Senate. This man\u2019s reply to Robert Hayne declared \u201cLiberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable!\u201d The 19th century \u201cGreat Triumvirate\u201d consisted of John Calhoun, Henry Clay, and, for ten points, what Massachusetts senator?", "answer": "Daniel<b> Webster</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Twenty-two baboons line the upper frieze of the larger of two structures in this complex, which was rediscovered by Jean-Louis Burckhardt and Giovanni Belzoni. The inner walls of this pair of structures align with the sun in February and October, illuminating statues of Ptah, Ra-Horakhty, Amun, and the pharaoh who constructed these temples. This portion of the Nubian Monuments was moved to protect it from flooding caused by the Aswan High Dam. For ten points, name this pair of Egyptian temples fronted by massive statues of Nefertari and Ramses II.", "answer": "<b> Abu Simbel</b> (prompt on \u201cNubian Monuments\u201d before it is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The losing general of this battle \u201chad not despaired of the Republic\u201d after escaping with seventy horsemen. In the aftermath of this battle, Tarentum and Capua revoked their</b> <b>allegiance with the loser. The winning side placed (+)</b> <b>Celtic and Spanish forces in the</b> <b>center, where they pulled back, allowing hidden, experienced Libyan soldiers to entrap the losing army in a double-envelopment. Gaius Terentius Varro survived this battle, though (*)</b> 70,000 Romans did not. Victories at Trebia and Lake Trasimene were followed by a massive defeat at, for ten points, what 216 BC battle in southern Italy, a massive tactical victor for Hannibal?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Cannae</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Karl Marx referred to this man as the \u201cmost miserable and meanest of blackguards.\u201dWhile Santiago Mari\u02dcno fought in the east, this man worked with Jos\u00b4e F\u00b4elix Ribas on</b> <b>the west to defeat an army led by Domingo de Monteverde. This man (+)</b> <b>wrote about</b> <b>the failures of the First Republic in an 1812 document; nine years later, his forces were victorious at the Battle of Carabobo, allowing this man to (*) </b> establish, and become the first president of, Gran Colombia. For ten points, name this South American \u201cLiberator,\u201d honored as the namesake of a country with capitals La Paz and Sucre.", "answer": "Simon<b> Bolivar</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this principality on the French Riviera, known for its casino at Monte Carlo.", "answer": "<b> Monaco</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This politician said that \u201cEvery good Christian ought to kick\u201d Jerry Falwell in support of Sandra Day O\u2019Connor. The \u201cA Time for Choosing\u201d speech supported one campaign of this man, who once called the Eisenhower administration a \u201cdime store New Deal.\u201d This</b> <b>man, who claimed that (+)</b> <b>\u201cextremism in defense of liberty is no vice,\u201d was the subject</b> <b>\u201cextremism in defense of liberty is no vice,\u201d was the subject</b> <b>of an ad featuring a little girl picking flower petals followed by a (*)</b> <b>of an ad featuring a little girl picking flower petals followed by a (*)</b> nuclear explosion. The \u201cDaisy\u201d ad targeted, for ten points, what Arizona Republican who lost in a landslide to Lyndon Johnson in 1964?", "answer": "Barry<b> Goldwater</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}